Finding Aid for Charles E. Potter Papers 1947-1958
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles E. Potter Papers 1947-1958
Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.
Republican U. S. Congressman from Lapeer, Michigan, 1946-1952; U.S. Senator, 1952-1959. Scrapbooks containing clippings, press releases, speeches, newsletters, and photographs; senatorial campaign files, 1952 and 1958; statements about state and national issues; files relating to legislation which he introduced; Potter's voting record in Congress; and photographs and motion pictures.
85444 AC, Aa 2, UAm, Ac
10 linear feet
2 oversize folders
11 oversize volumes
1 film reels
1.73 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mary Elizabeth Potter (Mrs. Charles E. Potter, donor no. 6437 ) in 1980.
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Charles E. Potter was born October 30, 1916 in Lapeer, Michigan. After graduating from Eastern Michigan University in 1938, he served as administrator of the Bureau of Social Aid for Cheboygan County. He enlisted in the army in 1942 and was seriously wounded in France in 1945 where he lost both lower limbs. After his discharge from the service in 1946, Potter was engaged as a vocational rehabilitation representative for the Retraining and Reemployment Administration. He resigned in 1947 following his election as a Republican to the United States Congress from the 11th District to the Eightieth Congress to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Frederick V. Bradley. Potter was twice reelected, to the Eighty-first and Eighty-second. While in the House, he served on the Un-American Activities Committee and gained a measure of notoriety for his role in reopening hearings on alleged communist influence in Hollywood. He also called for a separate investigation into alleged communist involvement in Michigan's labor organizations.
Potter resigned from the House in 1952 when he was elected to the United States Senate defeating Democratic appointee Blair Moody who had been selected following the death of Arthur H. Vandenberg. Potter was elected for the remaining two months of Vandenberg's term and won a full six-year term in the same election. As a senator, Potter as a member of the committee chaired by Joseph McCarthy began to inquire into allegations of impropriety by the Wisconsin senator and his staff. Potter also questioned the propriety of the relationship between Eisenhower advisor Sherman Adams and Boston industrialist Bernard Goldfine. Adams eventually resigned but some believe that Eisenhower was not fully supportive of Potter in his reelection bid in 1958 when he was defeated by Philip A. Hart. Potter spent the remainder of his career running a consulting firm for American and foreign companies. He died November 23, 1979.
The Potter collection, except for a copy of his 1965 account of the Army-McCarthy controversy, Days of Shame, begins with his first term in Congress following his election in 1947 and concludes with his defeat for reelection to the Senate in 1958. The collection includes a small series of Biographical/personal information followed by several files detailing his senate election campaigns in 1952 and 1958. Other series in the collection include Congressional Papers; Scrapbooks and Clippings; and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Great Lakes.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Old age.; Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.; Republican Party (Mich.); Shipping--Great Lakes.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1952.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1958.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; Veterans--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Broadcasting.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Handicapped persons.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Music.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Political elections--1956.; Political elections--1958.; Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.; Republican Party (Mich.); Saint Lawrence Seaway.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/personal
  - Book: Days of Shame, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Awards and citations (military, political and civic) (Box 1)
    (also in oversize folder Ac)
  - Articles (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
- Election Campaigns
  - Election of 1952
    - Campaign advertisements, cards and ephemera (Box 1)
    - Campaign program (Box 1)
    - Campaign speeches undated, May-November 1952, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Campaign press releases April-November 1952, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Issues (veterans' legislation) correspondence (Box 1)
    - Issues (miscellaneous) correspondence (Box 1)
    - Ethnic groups (Box 1)
    - Petitions (Box 1)
    - Campaign material and election certificates, 7 items (Box 1)
      (in oversize folder Ac)
  - Election of 1958
    - Campaign press releases August-November 1958, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Topical files
      - Advertising and ephemera (Box 1)
      - Contributors, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Election-challengers (Box 1)
      - Mailing lists (Box 1)
      - National Federation of Republican Women (Box 1)
      - Newspapers and radio campaign (Box 1)
      - Organization (Box 1)
      - Republican National Committee (Box 1)
      - Republican State Central Committee (Box 1)
      - Republican State Central Committee (violation of corrupt practices act) (Box 1)
      - Republican publications (Box 1)
      - State operating fund (Box 1)
      - Vote analyses 1956-1958 (Box 1)
      - Votes cost (primary) (Box 1)
    - Notebook containing lists and information about county Republican workers (Box 1)
- Congressional Papers
  Congressional Papers is the largest series in the collection and is comprised in part of Potter's public statements. These include news releases, radio and television broadcasts, and various speeches. This series also include legislative files that pertaining to specific pieces of legislation that Potter worked on or took an interest in while serving in the House and the Senate. This series concludes with files and volumes documenting Potter's voting record.
  - Public statements and related
    - News releases 1953-June 1956, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - News releases July 1956-August 1958, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Congressional Record tear-sheets 1958 (Box 2)
    - Radio and television broadcasts 1950-1957, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Statements 1953-1957, 6 folders (Box 2)
      (largely statements, speeches and correspondence about state and national issues)
    - Letters of appreciation from constituents and others 1952-1958, 11 folders (Box 2)
    - Audio-tapes, 3 reels (Box 2)
    - Senator Potter's Reports 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Audiotapes
    - College news conference, 1958 June 15, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
      - [Part 1], [85444-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Ruth Hagy interviews G. Mennen Williams for College News Conference. Williams is questioned on politics and Charles E. Potter.)
    - Senator Potter Quartette, 1958 March 25, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, ??
      - [Part 1], [85444-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (The Senator Potter Quartette sings three songs.)
    - Reception, Occidental Hotel, [Undated], Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, ??
      - [Part 1], [85444-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (Senator Potter answers questions from constituents about unemployment, farm bills, the status of the Republican party.)
  - Legislative files (bills arranged by Congress, Session, and Number)
    - 80th Congress: H. R. 5758: Armed Forces Leave Act of 1946 (Box 3)
    - 81st Congress
      - H. R. 961, etc.: Upper Peninsula Fish Hatchery (Box 3)
      - H. R. 5346: Long-range Shipping Bill (Box 3)
    - 82nd Congress:
      - H. R. J. 159: St. Lawrence Seaway (Box 3)
      - H. R. J. 242: Special National Election (Box 3)
      - H. R. 261: Bonus for Combat Troops (Box 3)
      - H. R. 1898: Authorization for Secretary of Commerce to compile statistical data relating to travel (Box 3)
      - H. R. 2995: To amend joint resolution regarding Great Lakes sea lampreys (Box 3)
      - H. R. 3180: Establish Federal Education Agency (Box 3)
      - H. R. 6500: To amend joint resolution regarding Great Lakes sea lampreys (Box 3)
    - 83rd Congress
      - Senate Congressional Resolution 40: To place inscription "United States of America" on export containers (Box 3)
      - S. J. Res. 95: John J. Pershing memorial (Box 3)
      - S. 1442: Federal Power Act (Box 3)
      - S. 2150: St. Lawrence Seaway (Box 3)
      - S. 3596: Federal Trade Commission Act (Box 3)
    - 84th Congress
      - S. 17: Repeal of manufacturers' excise tax on automobiles, etc. (Box 3)
      - S. Con. Res. 18: re. mental illness (Box 3)
      - S. J. Res.177: sale of certain war-built tankers (Box 3)
      - S. 693: Establishment of the United States Commission on the Aging and Aged, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - S. 771: Communications Act of 1934 (Box 3)
      - S. 1032: Great Lakes connecting channels above Lake Erie (Box 3)
      - S. 1381: To incorporate the Society of the 28th Division (Box 3)
      - S. 2707: To establish Technological laboratory under Fish and Wildlife Service to serve Great Lakes region (Box 3)
      - S. 3108: To encourage construction of modern Great Lakes bulk cargo vessels (Box 3)
      - S. 3447: To give effect to convention on Great Lakes Fisheries (Box 3)
      - S. 3617: re. prescribing criminal penalties for subversive activities (Box 3)
      - S. 4159: re. discrimination against ports on Great Lakes (Box 3)
      - S. 4174: re. excise tax on passenger automobiles (Box 3)
    - 85th Congress
      - S. Res. 17: re. section 2, rule XXII of the Standing Rules of the Senate (Box 3)
      - S. J. Res. 93: Sale of war-built vessels for servicing ports on Great Lakes (Box 3)
      - S. J. Res. 106: Commission to investigate utilization of radio and television frequencies, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - S. Res. 251: Opposing television broadcasting charges (Box 4)
      - S. 258: To establish a commission on the Aged and Aging (Box 4)
      - S. 534: To amend Merchant Marine Act 1936 (Box 4)
      - S. 551: To repeal manufacturers excise tax on autos and trucks (Box 4)
      - S. 901: To amend Agricultural Adjustment Act of 1938 (Box 4)
      - S. 902: To transfer certain lands to state of Michigan (Box 4)
      - S. 1223: National Cemetery at Fort Custer, Michigan (Box 4)
      - S. 1285: To incorporate Military Order of Purple Heart (Box 4)
      - S. 1440: To incorporate veterans of World War I (Box 4)
      - S. 1514: To amend Commodity Exchange Act to prohibit trading in onion futures (Box 4)
      - S. 1577: To repeal section of Communications Act of 1934 (Box 4)
      - S. 1598: re. restrictions on importation of hardwood plywood (Box 4)
      - S. 1695: To amend Internal Revenue Code of (tax revision for small business)1954 (deductions for teachers) (Box 4)
      - S. 1820: Tax relief for small business (Box 4)
      - S. 2624: Designation of the Wiley-Dondero lock (Box 4)
      - S. 2998: To amend Internal Revenue Code of 1954 (import tax on copper) (Box 4)
      - S. 3337: To amend Medals of Honor Act (acts of heroism on inland waterways vessels) (Box 4)
      - S. 3865: Distribution of automobiles in interstate commerce, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - S. 4177: Acquisition of site for Federal Building in Detroit (Box 4)
      - S. 4220: To provide for conveyance of certain lands to the state of Michigan (Box 4)
      - S. 4293: re. distribution and sale of complex mechanical products through small business (Box 4)
      - H. R. 8381: To amend Internal Revenue Code of 1954 (Box 4)
      - H. R. 13382: To amend Internal Revenue Code of 1954 (tax revision for small business) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous subject files
    - Lapeer dinner 1955 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with Ernest R. Breech (and enclosures) concerning Congressional investigating committees 1955 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Korean War Atrocities 1953 (Box 4)
    - Special Subcommittee on Investigation 1954 (Box 4)
    - Notebook re. hearings on status and development of UHF-TV channels (Box 4)
    - Michigan Minute Men for Eisenhower (Box 4)
    - Papers re. alleged members of Communist Party in Michigan (Box 4)
  - Speeches
    - "Eisenhower the Man," October 1, 1953 (Box 5)
    - "How Can We Make America Invulnerable," October 5, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Mutual Security (Harry Dexter White) July 30, 1954 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Voting record and form responses
    - Voting record notebooks 1953-1958 (arranged by subject) (Box 5)
    - Voting record (correspondence and other materials concerning Senate voting record) 1952-1958, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Voting record (miscellaneous), 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Form responses to constituent correspondence (partially indexed) (Box 5)
    - Voting Record 1941-1958 (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks and newspaper clippings
  Scrapbooks and newspaper clippings is a series that includes volumes of chronologically arranged newspaper accounts of Potter and his activities, and other volumes containing copies of press releases, speeches, newsletters, and radio and television broadcasts.
  - Scrapbooks containing copies of press releases, speeches, radio and television broadcasts, and newsletters 1949-1957 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks containing copies of press releases, speeches, radio and television broadcasts, and newsletters 1957-1958 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook containing Congressional Record excerpts, 1948-1950, 1957-1958 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks containing clippings, etc
    - Vol. 1 1947-1948 (Volume 1)
    - Vol. 2 1949-1950 (Volume 2)
    - Vol. 3 1951-1952 (Volume 3)
    - Vol. 4 1952 (Volume 4)
    - Vol. 5 1953-1954 (Volume 5)
    - Vol. 6 December 1952-November 1954 (Volume 6)
    - Vol. 7 1955-1956 (Volume 7)
    - Vol. 8 1955-1956 (Volume 8)
    - Vol. 9 1957-1958 (Volume 9)
    - Vol. 10 1957 (Volume 10)
    - Vol. 11 January-March 1958 (Volume 11)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - 1952, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - 1958, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - March 1958 (outstate) (Box 9)
    - April 1958 (Box 9)
    - Apr.1958 (outstate) (Box 9)
    - May 1958 (outstate) (Box 9)
    - June 1958 (Box 9)
    - June 1958 (outstate), 2 folders (Box 9)
    - July 1958 (Box 10)
    - July 1958 (outstate), 2 folders (Box 10)
    - August 1958 (Box 10)
    - August 1958 (outstate) (Box 10)
    - September-October 1958 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous; loose clippings from scrapbooks (Box 10)
- Visual materials
  The final series - Visual Materials - includes both photographs and motion pictures. These materials related primarily to Potter's political career, including photos of Joseph McCarthy's investigating committee, photos and campaign commercials from the 1956 and 1958 elections, photos and a film relating to physically handicapped people, and a film of a singing group promoting the St. Lawrence Seaway.
  - Photographs
    (also in oversize folder UAm)
    - Chronological
      - 1947-1952 (Box 10)
      - 1953 (Box 10)
      - 1954 (Box 10)
      - 1955 (Box 10)
      - 1956
        - Lewis E. Berry swearing-in (Box 10)
        - Eisenhower reelection campaign (Box 10)
        - Presentation of silver star, etc (Box 10)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
      - 1957 (Box 10)
      - 1958
        - Mackinac Bridge dedication (Box 10)
        - Reelection campaign (Life Magazine photos) (Box 10)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Topical
      - Campaign and publicity photos undated (Box 10)
      - Groups undated, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - McCarthy hearings (television photos) (Box 10)
      - Mrs. Potter (Box 10)
      - Portraits (Box 10)
      - Portraits of others (Box 10)
      - Presidents Truman and Eisenhower (Box 10)
      - Vice President Nixon (Box 10)
    - Negatives (Box 10)
  - Films, all films are 16mm black and white sound
    - Campaign commercials 1958
      - "Barber shop", 20 seconds (Box 10)
      - "Congressional record", 60 seconds (Box 10)
      - "I stand on my record", 8 seconds (Box 10)
      - "Lorraine Potter", 20 seconds (Box 10)
      - "Lorraine Potter", 60 seconds (Box 10)
      - "Man in the street" (Box 10)
      - "Spot the question mark" (Box 10)
    - Eisenhower press conference October 1, 1958 (Box 10)
    - Quarternotes sing for the St. Lawrence Seaway, with Sen. Potter's remarks March 7, 1958 (Box 10)
    - "First Federal Presents..." (Sen. Potter and Sen. Green discussing aid for the handicapped) June 1, 1958 (Reel 1)